<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>MakeTronica</title>
    <description>Make something, preferably incorporating moving electrons.</description>
    <link>http://maketronica.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://maketronica.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2016 20:44:00 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 May 2016 20:44:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Solar Powered Beehives, Take 2</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m made a major modification to the power I’m running to the electronic sensors in our 2 beehives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I originally ran power to each of the hives, I ran everything off of a single USB port on the solar charge controller. I was concerned at the time that that might not be sufficient to power two Raspberry Pis, two Arduinos, and all of the sensors I’m hooking up. That appears to be true as I’ve been having trouble keeping everything running consistently for long periods of time.  So, I made some significant changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parts List:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1VWIDzl&quot;&gt;Solar Starter Kit&lt;/a&gt; (The exact one I used isn’t available anymore, but this appears to be a good alternative.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1VWIRX1&quot;&gt;Deep Cycle Battery Valve&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1VWJjVm&quot;&gt;Switching Regulator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/22uxBkX&quot;&gt;Low Voltage Outdoor Lighting Wire&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1RrzAEN&quot;&gt;Terminal Block&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1nXLqJ2&quot;&gt;Terminal Block Jumpers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1RrzSeO&quot;&gt;Junction Box&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1RrzVr5&quot;&gt;Micro USB Cables&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;====================&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solar charge controller provides 12 volts, but the Raspberry Pis and Arduinios all require 5 volts.  There are lots of different ways to step voltage from 12 volts down to 5, and the most popular for this type of project would probably be a 7805 voltage regulator, which can usually be found online for around 50 - 60 cents each, plus shipping.  The downside to using 7805s is that, to do the job, they use a fair amount of extra energy.  Often this isn’t a big deal, but if you’re trying to run off of a battery or solar power (as I am), then it can be a big problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Switching regulators, such as these, accomplish their task in a completely different way than the 7805s and don’t use nearly as much energy.  Switching regulators come in lots of different styles, but what I particularly like about these is that they’re specifically designed to be a drop in replacement for the 7805s. If you’re used to using 7805s, then you can probably switch to these without making any changes to your circuit, much less learning about a whole new component.  The downside, however, is that instead of costing 50 cents, these particular switching regulators currently cost $12-14 apiece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin, I disconnected a bunch of what I’d done in the previous video to try to start with a bit of a clean slate.  I left the junction boxes under each hive in place as they won’t really be changing.  I’ll be running 12 volts instead of just 5 through each one, but most of the wiring will be identical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I brought in a new storage locker to keep the solar charge controller and battery in.  I felt like this looks better than the tub I was using, and it’ll definitely do a better job of protecting the contents from the weather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I drilled a hole in the handle from the inside in such a way as to protect it from rain getting in.  There were already some small ventilation holes nearby, so I figured it was as good a spot as any.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I ran the cable from the solar panels though the hole from outside the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I took the cable from the first junction box that used to plug into the USB port on the solar charge controller, cut off the USB connector, and then drilled another hole in the locker to run that cable through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solar charge controller has three places to connect to on the bottom.  One for the solar panels themselves, one for the battery, and the last one is for the load.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only one of the two wires on the cable I’m using has writing on it, and since I need to maintain consistent polarity throughout the circuit, I had earlier decided arbitrarily to use the writing on the cable as a guide to which wire would be positive (the one without writing), and which would be negative or ground (the one with writing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stripped the ends of the cable coming from the hive junction box and attached it as the load, being careful to match up the wire with writing on it to the negative terminal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I went back to the first junction box and disconnected the wire that I’d previously run up to the first hive.  This cable currently has a micro USB connector attached to the other end to plug into the Raspberry Pi.  But now I’m going to be running 12 volts through here, so instead this cable will need to run to one of the switching regulators, instead of directly to the Pi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took the cable into my office and cut the USB connector off, identified which wire had writing on it, and soldered a black 22 gauge solid wire to the end, and shrunk some heat-shrink tubing around the solder joint.  This wire is the right size to plug directly into the breadboard inside the electronics box.  Then I did the same thing with a red wire for the positive side (the wire without writing on it).  Finally, I shrunk a larger piece of heat-shrink tubing around the entire thing, just for good measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I went back out to the junction box to re-connect the cable, once again, making sure to match wires with writing on them, to wires with writing on them, and visa versa.  In the earlier version of this project, I’d already attached the terminal block jumpers in such a way that half of the terminal block could all be wired to positive, and the other half to negative, giving me plenty of options to distribute power wherever I may need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I went into the electronics box for the first hive, and plugged one of the switching regulators into the breadboard.  Then I plugged a 22 gauge black wire into the breadboard next to the center pin, and a red wire next to the left most pin.  These will carry ground and 5 volts over to the Arduino and all of the sensors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I connected the male end of black and red male/female jumpers next to the same pins.  These will carry ground and 5 volts to corresponding GPIO pins on the Raspberry Pi.   Keep in mind though that powering the Raspberry Pi through the GPIO pins like this bypasses circuit protections that are built into the Pi, but I’ll fix that in just a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I was finally able to connect the wire coming up from the junction box.  First I attached the black ground wire to the middle pin on the regulator, and then attached the red wire, which will be carrying 12 volts, to the left most pin. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I went back to the locker and hooked up the battery to the charge controller.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I needed to connect the solar panels.  Unfortunately, both of the cables coming from the panels were black, so there was no visible cue as to which was positive, and which was negative.  So, I grabbed my multimeter and measured across the two wires.  If I got a positive voltage, then I knew I had them right.  If I got a negative voltage, then I knew they were backward.  Easy-peasy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I knew which was which, I connected them to the solar charge controller as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that seems to have solved my power issues. Everything has been running much more reliably since made this change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran a test to find out how long the hives could last on just battery power by disconnecting the solar panels from the charge controller.  I got a little over two days of power out of the battery.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, right when I was ready to plug things back in and charge the battery back up, the weather got cloudy and rainy for a week, and it wasn’t charging up enough during the day to last all night. This causes me concern that the solar panels and battery won’t be able to keep things running 24 - 7 through the winter, when we have very short days and tend to have lots of clouds to boot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get the battery back up to full capacity for the time being, I ran a long extension cord from the hour out to the hives and plugged in our trickle charger for our car batteries and connected that up to the battery along with the solar charge controller.  That got things back to normal until the weather improves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still had one more small change I wanted to to make in the hives though, just for safety’s sake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll recall that I ran 5 volts and ground directly to the GPIO pins on the Raspberry Pi, and that I mentioned that doing so bypasses the circuit protections built into the Pi.  Well, I realized that I still had the micro-usb ends of the USB cables that I’d cut up for the earlier version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, once again, I exposed the red and black wires from the cut end of the cable.  I’ll only be using this for power still, so I don’t care about the other wires.  I soldered up two 22 gauge wires, matching the colors, and protected the joints with a couple layers of heatshrink tubing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I disconnected the 12 volt line coming into the switching regulator,  replaced the two jumpers going from the 5 volt and ground pins on the switching regulator to the GPIO pins with the new cable, this time plugging the other end into the micro-usb port on the Raspberry Pi, and then reconnected the 12 volt line.  This allows the Raspberry Pi’s built in voltage protections to feel needed and appreciated once again, and we all like to feel needed and appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still a few more things I want to add to the beehives, including ambient temperature and humidity sensors, and cameras and microphones inside the hives, among other things. Oh, and of course, bees. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://maketronica.com/solar-powered-beehives-take-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maketronica.com/solar-powered-beehives-take-2/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Beehive Automatic Water Supply</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently made an automatically refilling water supply for our two beehives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When keeping bees in an urban setting, it’s important to make sure they have a
reliable source of water. One way or another, they’ll find water, and I wanted
to try to provide our bees with an option more preferable than a neighborhood
swimming pool or bird bath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parts List:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1YstR0r&quot;&gt;Planter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1YstT8v&quot;&gt;Float Valve&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/23sJnjP&quot;&gt;Tubing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I disassembled the float so that I could figure out what size drill bit to use.
I needed a hole just big enough to fit the one end of the float through, and no
bigger. It turned out that my half inch drill bit was just a little too small,
but the next size up I had was too big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I used my too-small bit to drill a hole in the side of the planter, and then
grabbed a file to make the whole just a little bigger, trying to be careful to
keep the hole round, with limited success. Once the hole was big enough, I
stuck the float through from the inside and reassembled it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I attached the ¼” tubing, the other end of which will simply plug into our
drip irrigation system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then I put in a bunch of rocks, and took it out to our hives.  If you do
this, I recommend taking it out to the hives, and &lt;strong&gt;then&lt;/strong&gt;putting
in a bunch of rocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I hooked it up to water, and tested it out. It filled up just fine, but
then I noticed that it was leaking pretty good right where the float attached
to the planter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I drained it all out and inspected things, and that’s when I realized that a
support structure on the planter was causing the float to sit a little crooked
and not seal properly. So I used a knife to trim that piece down a bit, and
then tried filling it up again.  This time there were no leaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I piled the rocks into a bit of an island near the center of the planter, and
then stuck a bunch of sticks (some of which I borrowed from our neighbor’s
cherry tree) into the rocks to give the bees another way to crawl down to the
water and back out again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the rock island and the sticks, I hope that it won’t matter what level the
water is at (as long as it’s not empty). The bees should always have a few
options to get to the surface comfortably, without needing to take a swim. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However there’s one very minor problem still. I can’t seem to position the
planter such that the float properly turns the water on and off. Our yard isn’t
completely level, and when the end of the plant with the float is a little high,
the water continues to trickle in very very slowly, until the planter starts to
overflow. However, if I raise the other end of the planter up just a little bit,
the float will turn off the water when the planter is full, but then never turn
the water back on again when the lever drops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe there are some adjustments I can make to make it work better. However,
since this will be attached to a drip irrigation system on a timer, I’m not too
worried about it occasionally overfilling.  That seems to help drain out
floaters that get blown in by the wind anyway. If you have any ideas for how to
improve on this though, please leave a comment below.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://maketronica.com/beehive-automatic-water-supply/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maketronica.com/beehive-automatic-water-supply/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Electronic Beehive Scale</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post I’ll show you how I made scales to take regular electronic
 measurements of the weights of our soon-to-be-occupied beehives using a load
 cell and an Arduino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In previous posts, I showed how I made the electronics box that holds the
Arduino and Raspberry Pi, ran solar power to each of the hives, and added
temperature and humidity sensors to the electronics box and the brood box. Now
it’s time to add the scales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing the weight of of a beehive as an indicator of how much honey they’ve
collected gives important clues as to the health of the colony without pulling
the entire hive apart. Some beekeepers have impressive tools that they use to
manually weigh their hives… but that’s not my style.  I want to know, right
now, how much each hive weighs, and how it’s changed recently, while I’m
eating breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be interested in weighing something other than a beehive, and you’re
in luck. The process I’ll demonstrate here could easily be applied to other
projects as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parts List:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1V2ViQ3&quot;&gt;Load Cell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/239a21e&quot;&gt;Socket Cap Screws&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/239a752&quot;&gt;Galvanized Hinge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/239afl7&quot;&gt;Hx711 Amplifier&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1RUTh2c&quot;&gt;Sainsmart UNO R3&lt;/a&gt; (Arduino compatible)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First I measured and cut down some 2x4’s to make into frames that will fit
underneath the hives.  Two frames will make up one scale.  I also needed one
shorter piece per scale that will fit inside the lower frame for one end of
the load cell to attach to.  Lastly, I cut a couple of 1x4s to cover up one
end of the load cell and protect it from the weather. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I measured and marked where to cut a slot in the very center of one side
of one of the frames for the load cell to fit into.  It’s ok to make the slot
a little bigger than the load cell, so that it easily slides in. But it’s
important to precisely measure where the center of the slot is, to be able to
accurately measure where to drill the holes for the screws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also need to cut a similar slot into the cross piece that the other end of
the load cell will attach to, simply because my screws aren’t long enough to
go all the way through the 2x4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I clamped the boards down, cut out the slots with a jigsaw, and then
checked to see that the load cell would fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I measured where to drill the holes for the screws. I needed the screws
to line up precisely with the load cell, so it was very important to get this
exactly right. I measured that the holes in the load cell were 15 cm apart
(measured from the left side of one hole, to the left side of the next). So, I
marked my holes along a lengthwise center line I’d measured, 7.5 cm off on
either side of the center of the notch I cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I went to the drill press, clamped my board down and very carefully lined
up the board to the bit making sure that I was right on center.  Then, I
drilled each of the holes, hoping that I got close enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I measured how far down I needed to drill with a slightly larger bit so
that I could countersink the screw heads, and marked the bit with some blue
tape. These holes were much easier to drill since I didn’t need to be nearly
so precise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I held my breath, hoping that everything would line up right, and
attached the two ends of the load cell to their respective boards.  Even
though I hadn’t practiced this with some scrap wood ahead of time at all
(cough, cough) everything lined up just perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I assembled the frames around the load cell assembly, using clamps to try
to keep things semi-square.  It’s not a perfect system, but it’s close enough
for this job. The hardest part was getting the last corner of each frame to
line up, but some clamps, brute force, and a rubber mallet got it there. Unlike
the screw holes, this really only needs to be squarish, but it’s still good to
be as precise as is reasonably possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the two frames were individually assembled, I could tested that they
would fit together with the load cell assembly, but I didn’t want to attach
that part quite yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First I need to add the hinges to attach each frame together.  This end of the
scale will end up supporting about half the weight of the hive, giving the load
cell itself an effective capacity of 200 kg, instead of just 100.  It was
important to make sure there was a slight gap between each of the frames so
that they would move freely and not rub against each other or the hinges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At last, it was time to attach the inside cross piece of the load cell assembly
to the bottom frame. In order for the load cell to do it’s job, I didn’t want
the top frame resting on the bottom frame, as the load cell needs to bear the
entire weight. So, I used the handle of my rubber mallet to create a small gap
between the two frames before drilling pilot holes and screwing the cross
piece to the bottom frame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I attached the 1x4 to the end to cover up the load cell and protect it
from the weather and painted the outside of the entire thing in a few coats of
exterior paint.  I didn’t paint the inside or the load cell as it should be
protected from the weather by the beehive.  How well that works out remains to
be seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hx711 load cell amplifier came without it’s headers soldered on, so I
needed to do that first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I brought in the electronics from one of the hives to add the amplifier to
the breadboard.  Due to the size of the amplifier, I ran some jumpers from
underneath it out to where I could more easily connect to, doing the same with
5v and ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I belatedly realized that I had 5v and ground rails right there next to
the amplifier, and so re-ran those jumpers right to where they needed to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I ran the signal and clock lines from the amplifier over to the arduino,
and connected up the 4 wires on the load cell to the other side of the
amplifier, red to E+, black to E-, green to A- and white to A+.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to an &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sparkfun/HX711-Load-Cell-Amplifier/blob/master/firmware/SparkFun_HX711_Calibration/SparkFun_HX711_Calibration.ino&quot;&gt;Arduino sketch from Sparkfun&lt;/a&gt;
to help calibrate the scale. First I had to change the pins defined in the
sketch to those that I’d actually plugged into.  With the scale empty, I
uploaded the script to the arduino, and then placed some known weights on the
scale once things got going. Then I adjusted the calibration factor in the
sketch and started over until it was reading in the right ballpark.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author of the sketch found a calibration factor of negative 7050 worked
best for him.  In my case, positive 13,500 was more appropriate.  Depending on
your load cell and scale, you may find that a setting even more different than
either of ours works best for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully though, both of my scales worked good enough at 13,500, so I didn’t
need to do any special coding in my hivebot sketches to take into account
different calibration factors for the different hives.  If you’re also building
multiple identical scales, you may or may not not be so lucky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At last I was ready to take the scales out the hives. I moved the hive aside
before placing the scale underneath, with the load cell toward the rear of the
hive. Then I reassembled the hive on top of the scale and replaced the
breadboard and arduino back in the electronics box on top, re-connected the
raspberry pi and the other sensors, and put the roof back on, and then did the
same with the other scale on the other hive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scale on the first hive turned out to be surprisingly level.  Maybe the
cinder blocks are a little high in the front.  However, the second hive was
tilting way forward. So, I just cut up a piece of scrap wood to place under
the front of the hive to level things back out again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relevant bits of the hivebot arduino sketch for the scale include the
constants that define which pins are connected to the load cell amplifier, as
well as the calibration factor and zero factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally, one would code a sketch like this to re-tare (or zero) the scale
whenever the sketch starts up, but I can’t be removing several hundred pounds
of active beehive every time I need to restart the arduino, but the zero factor
gets around this.  The calibration sketch I used above prints tares the scale
and then prints out the zero factor. So, I can use this to zero the scale when
the arduino starts up, without removing the load from the scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next in the sketch, I initialize the scale, telling it which two pins to
monitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within setup, I set the calibration and zero factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, within the loop, I simply ask the scale periodically for the units,
which I earlier calibrated to be pounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s it.  Both scales have now been reading the weights of our two, still
unoccupied, beehives for a little over a week. I’ve posted &lt;a href=&quot;/hivebot&quot;&gt;live charts of the
data generated from the beehives&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things to keep in mind.  Over long periods of measurement, load cells are
highly subject to temperature drift… and being outside like this will only make
that worse. Furthermore, due to the fact that these scale frames are made of
wood, humidity and other factors will likely affect the accuracy as well.  So,
I’m not expecting to know, to the ounce, exactly how much the hives weigh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, over the past week, with no changes to what the scales are weighing,
the scales have maintained readings within a range of about 1 pound, with some
warm days and cold nights, so I’m feeling pretty good about that. The
approximate changes in weight that these scales will provide from day to day
and week to week should tell me what I want to know, even if they’re not
accurate to the ounce, and be a lot better than manually weighing the hives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The load cells are pretty sheltered from the weather inside the frames, but
it’ll be interesting to see how they hold up over the course of a year. Maybe
next spring I’ll be able to get down in there and have a look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for watching.  In upcoming posts, I plan to be adding one more
temperature and humidity sensor, this time for ambient readings outside the
hive, an infrared camera and microphone inside the broodbox, and an automatic
refilly water supply for the bees.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://maketronica.com/electronic-beehive-scale/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maketronica.com/electronic-beehive-scale/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Beehive Temperature and Humidity Sensors</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I installed another temperature and humidty sensor in the broodbox of our
beehives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I created a cage out of 1/8” wire mesh (to protect the sensor from propolis)
and installed it into one of the hive frames.  This makes it easy to remove for
maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I soldered the sensor, a resistor, and some wires to a small project
board, and attached some cardboard to the back to protect it from shorting out
against the wire mesh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I put the assembly inside the cage on the frame, and placed the whole
thing into the broodbox in the beehive, like any other frame except this one
has wires hanging out of the beehive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I connected the signal wire to the Arduino in the electronics box, and
wired the 5 volt and ground wires into the junction box beneath the hive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Live charts of sensor data available on the &lt;a href=&quot;/hivebot&quot;&gt;Hivebot page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parts List:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1LwoMmE&quot;&gt;1/8” Wire Mesh Screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1ZbVpIq&quot;&gt;Temp/Humidity Sensor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/21CpDnB&quot;&gt;Prototype PCB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1RUTh2c&quot;&gt;Sainsmart UNO R3&lt;/a&gt; (Arduino compatible)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1ZbVETF&quot;&gt;Raspberry Pi 2 Model B&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://maketronica.com/broodbox_sensor_cage/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maketronica.com/broodbox_sensor_cage/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Solar Powered Beehives</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I ran solar power to our two beehives to run the Raspberry Pi’s, Arduinos,
and environmental sensors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran low voltage outdoor lighting wire from the solar panels to junction boxes
under each hive. On the end of the wire that ran to the solar panels, I atteched
one half of a USB cable to plug in to the usb port on the solar charge controller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran another cable from each juntion box up to the electronics box on the
beehives and attached the other (micro) end of the USB cables to it to plug in
to the Raspberry Pis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parts List:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/22uxBkX&quot;&gt;Low Voltage Outdoor Lighting Wire&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1RrzAEN&quot;&gt;Terminal Block&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1nXLqJ2&quot;&gt;Terminal Block Jumpers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1RrzSeO&quot;&gt;Junction Box&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1RrzVr5&quot;&gt;Micro USB Cables&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://maketronica.com/solar-powered-beehives/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maketronica.com/solar-powered-beehives/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hivebot Brain - Adding first sensors to a beehive</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working up to this for a while, and it’s finally coming together,
and not a moment too soon. The bees will be arriving in a little over a month
and I’ve still got a lot of work to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought the precut boards to make a shallow box to put on top of the beehive
to keep the core electronics in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I inserted some 1/8” wire mesh into the bottom of the box to allow airflow
but to keep the bees out of the electronics.  I don’t want them coating the
Raspberry Pi and Arduino in propolis.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, I’m putting the first temperature and humidity sensor on a breadboard
while I’m still figuring out how I want everything placed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parts List: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1LwoMmE&quot;&gt;1/8” Wire Mesh Screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1RUT7Yz&quot;&gt;Breadboard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1ZbVpIq&quot;&gt;Temp/Humidity Sensor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1RUTh2c&quot;&gt;Sainsmart UNO R3&lt;/a&gt; (Arduino compatible)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/1ZbVETF&quot;&gt;Raspberry Pi 2 Model B&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More info is available on &lt;a href=&quot;/hivebot&quot;&gt;the official hivebot page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://maketronica.com/hivebot-brain/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maketronica.com/hivebot-brain/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>3D Printing an RFID Antenna Coil Bobbin</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After figuring out how to create a custom wound RFID antenna for the ID-3LA RFID reader connected to an Arduino, I gave a shot at designing a 3D printable bobbin to wind the antenna onto.  I was hoping for more range than I got, but otherwise, it worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/maketronica/rfid_bobbin&quot;&gt;OpenSCAD Files&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shapeways.com/shops/maketronica3d&quot;&gt;Ready to wind bobbins&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://maketronica.com/3d-printing-rfid-antenna-coil/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maketronica.com/3d-printing-rfid-antenna-coil/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Increasing Arduino Digital Outputs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Increasing the number of digital outputs on an Arduino, on a massive scale, is a lot easier than you might think.  In these two videos I go through to process of wiring up the chip and writing code to activate the new outputs, and then I daisy chain 5 shift registers together to individually control 40 different digital outputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-1&quot;&gt;Part 1:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cAT07gy4DII&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-2&quot;&gt;Part 2:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RjzmKYg66nM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The library mentioned in the second video is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/maketronica/MultiShiftRegister&quot;&gt;available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a schematic that you may find helpful showing two shift registers daisy chained toghether.  To add more, just follow the same pattern as the second one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://maketronica.com/images/increase_arduino_outputs/schematic1_schem.png&quot; alt=&quot;Schematic with one shift register&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://maketronica.com/increase-arduino-digital-outputs/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maketronica.com/increase-arduino-digital-outputs/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Holiday Lightshow - Glorious Dawn</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is our holiday lightshow for 2015. I worked on this off and on for the better part of the year, and managed to get to all working just in time for Thanksgiving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://maketronica.com/holiday-lightshow-glorious-dawn/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maketronica.com/holiday-lightshow-glorious-dawn/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Calibrating an RFID antenna.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you have access to an oscilloscope, calibrating an RFID antenna is pretty easy.  To find out how to make an RFID antenna first, see &lt;a href=&quot;/making-an-rfid-antenna/&quot;&gt;my previous post&lt;/a&gt; on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wound up another RFID antenna like I did in the previous post, but this time I skipped the part where I took it off the PVC pipe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took the pipe with the antenna and the Arduino down to our local makerspace to use one of their oscilloscopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I connected the scope in parallel to the antenna and the chip, and used a 10X probe on channel one on the scope. I knew things were hooked up right when I could see a 70V-peak 125khz sine wave on the scope (your voltate will probably be different, but the frequency should not).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To determine if the coil had too much, or too little, inductance, I used a large magnet and brought it close to the antenna while watching the scope. If the voltage on the scope decreases, then the coil has too much inductance. If, on the other hand, it increases, then… you guessed it, there’s too little inductance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add (or remove) inductance, you simply need to remove (or add) turns to/from the coil.  Pay attention here.  If the voltage decreases, you need to add inductance, so you remove turns (unwind some wire).  However, if the voltage increases, you need to remove inductance, so you add more turns (wind more wire) onto the coil. Perhaps an easier way to remember is that the voltage indicates what you need to do. If it increases, add more turns.  If it decreses, remove turns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would recommend not adding or removing more than one turn at a time, and as you get closer to proper calibration, you likely only be adding or removing wire a quarter turn at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, I had too much inductance, so I had to unwind some wire. From this point it’s just a matter of adding and removing turns, in smaller and smaller increments, while you try to zero in to a point where the voltage on the scope doesn’t change when you bring the magnet close to your coil. Easy peasy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was done, the range on the antenna improved by 50%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you figure out any tricks to get a better calibration, please post a comment below.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://maketronica.com/calibrating-an-rfid-antenna/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://maketronica.com/calibrating-an-rfid-antenna/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
